there's this Plucky little podcaster
that you probably have never heard of
but his name is Joe Rogan on his podcast
he interviewed a famous YouTuber called
Derek actually his YouTube channel is
called uh more plates more dates it's a
long story as to why it's called that so
we just won't get into it but Derek
creates a lot of bodybuilding and hormon
related content and has honestly a
massive following in that recent podcast
they discussed creatine and some pretty
baffling things so I thought I would
touch on the science as we cover
multiple claims by the infamous Joe
Rogan and the broad shoulder Derek let's
get into it have you seen the studies on
Creatine and performance with uh sleep
deprivation very interesting another
thing that not being tested for which I
don't think it should be but like
creatin adequate doses interestingly for
years we all been told take your five
grams and you're good but what's often
not talked about is the fact that that
dosage is not going to be widespread the
optimal one for every single person you
will likely achieve muscle saturation
with that dose but it doesn't mean
you're going to get the full Suite of
benefits depending on your genetics how
much you weigh muscle mass metabolism so
five grams for a 140 PB person versus a
240 pound yeah so like some Studies have
found uh increased benefits up to like
20 gram a day okay let's put on the
brakes here because there's already two
things to discuss one Joe that's the
bald guy with the unkknown
podcast very briefly mentions that
creatine is beneficial for sleep
deprivation did he pull that out of
somewhere
unpleasant no there's uh some evidence
that's true dating back actually quite a
few years however a very recent study
took a more in-depth look in that
context and also identified benefits in
people who were sleep deprived
fascinatingly while we generally think
of creatine as a supplement that needs
to build up in our tissues this study
only gave a single dose and showed
benefit so a real quick takeaway is that
if you know that you'll be sleep
deprived on a particular night consider
a creatine to help you through the next
day especially if it's requires some
level of cognitive work the second thing
was mentioned by Derek the non-bal guy
saying that a typical 5 G recommended to
people may not be enough because of a
person's size genetics and so on May
play a factor I will say while it's true
that 5 GRS might be insufficient for
some people it'll be sufficient for the
vast majority of people at least from a
physical performance perspective as
Derek mentioned saturating the
musculature he then mentions that some
studies use up to 20 grams per day I
would push back against this uh slightly
not because I don't think that there
might be something to that in fact I
said the very same thing a year ago in
this video on Creatine but I also
mentioned there's no actual evidence
beyond the fact that some studies use 20
gram per day and show Effectiveness that
doesn't actually prove that there's an
additional benefit over 5 G we would
need specific studies to tease out those
differences
so it's a possibility but it's not
backed by the appropriate science yet
and then there's two types right there's
creatine monohydrate and then there's
another Cre what is the other one
there's different formats but some are
like HCL is essentially just bound to um
HCL instead of monohydrate which could
be more tolerable for somebody who gets
GI distress from
monohydrate thought to be you know water
solubility and other things but in
general monohydrated the one that has
the most literature supporting it is
tried and true it's cheaper easier to
access yeah so they're discussing
different chemical formulas of creatine
they look like this they're similar but
are bound to a water molecu or a
hydrochloric acid overall creatine
monohydrate is definitely the more
readily available one it tends to be
cheaper and it's equally effective as
the HCL formulation evidence in this
study there might be some benefits of
alternate versions of creatine compared
to the popular monohydrate formulation
because monohydrate can cause some
stomach discomfort but you can also just
uh avoid that by spreading consumption
throughout the day or using a micronized
version I took that from my extensive
research I did in my book that I wrote
on Creatine I don't sell it anymore but
it is well sourced only way to get it
now is through the physionic Insiders
along with full access to all my work
Linked In the description don't tell me
you didn't see that plug coming anyway
the takeaway here is to just buy the
cheapest creatine that you can find
usually that's creatine monohydrate this
next one is a meat lovers envy and a
plant-based nightmare so you have how
much meat per
day multiple pounds multiple cooked we
yeah yeah yeah wow yeah I probably at
least three pounds of meat A Day H yeah
yeah you might be getting I forget how
many pounds of meat you need to saturate
creatine stores or at least the
equivalent to five grams but you'd
probably still benefit from trying
supplementing more so that's a lot of
meat uh it does depend on the meat too I
had a tough time finding reputable
sources for this but according to the
University of Delaware which we all know
is the Harvard of Delaware they state
that beef pork and several types of fish
provide between 1.4 and 2.3 G of
creatine per pound so by those numbers
Joe that's the bald guy with the
minuscule podcast is probably getting
over five grams just from food however
for those that have asked me in the past
if they eat meat do they still need to
supplement the answer is likely yes
unless you're eating a majority meat
diet the takeaway here is that you need
to be supplementing with creatine as you
are unlikely to be getting enough from
food alone one of the most slept on
supplements for sure I think it kind of
got uh I don't know like not as much
attention as it deserves maybe more
recently it's gotten a bit more hyp
because of some of the literature around
its cognitive effects and whatnot but
it's like super useful for a myriad of
things okay this is merely opinion but I
disagree creatine has gotten a ton of
attention for many years I think it's
one that's been discussed a lot and many
people know about it now at least people
in the fitness space which is a lot of
people I could be biased because I'm
always exposed to content on it and
studies on it but that's the way that I
see it actually what's your impression
did you already know about creatine if
not I completely failed to introduce it
in this video so I royally screwed up
and you're completely confused on what
we're even talking about well it's a
molecule produced by your body and we
don't produce enough to saturate our
cells so many people although not all
benefit from supplementing with it as a
series of proposed health and
performance benefits as we'll discuss
next what is the mechanism for it giving
you a cognitive uh enhancing benefit I
think it's thought to be like local
energy production in the brain so some
people genetically or as they age or
what have you have deficiencies and the
capacity to produce ATP and if you can
like backfill it with like a readily
available source of phosphor then
you could basically get it to Baseline
of where it should be I'm not going to
go full physic on you and dive too deep
into this but a brief re explanation of
what Derek the guy with the hair uh said
it's true that as we age our cells can
become less able to generate cellular
energy known as ATP in such case
creatine can act as a reservoir of
energy by holding on to a critical
molecule called a phosphate when
creatine is holding on to a phosphate
it's called phosphocreatine which is
what Derek mentioned phosphocreatine can
donate phosphates to spent ATP molecules
called ADP and return them to their
fully energized ATP molecule it's
basically a backup Energy System there's
way way more to get get into for
creatine but I'll leave it to my other
content to get into those details people
that are on a vegan diet like what what
are their creatine levels like oh not
good enough for sure there's no way
right oh it's impossible even if you're
somebody who eats a lot of meat you
might think you're good but unless
you're eating multiple pounds a day it's
unlikely that you've saturated stores
they make a passing comment about people
using a vegan diet or primarily
plant-based diet and how it's impossible
for them to have sufficient creatine
levels in fact Studies have shown this
by switching people to a vegetarian diet
and even that less restrictive diet
people experience a reduction in bodily
stores of creatine so yes it's likely
even more important for people who don't
eat much meat to consume Creatine
assuming that they want the benefits of
creatine overall although Joe spreads a
lot of bad information fortunately he
has a minuscule podcast listened to by
two or three guys in Florida I think
this exchange with Derek here was
actually pretty good the takeaway is
that creatine is a worthy supplement to
consider for a number of reasons from
sleep deprivation physical performance
and cognitive benefits but the
intricacies of creatine extend Way
Beyond what I shallowly covered in this
video there's so much cool research
surrounding creatine that I begin
detailing here I promise you haven't
heard many of the things I mention in
these videos right here see you there
[Music]